// referencing to display hard coded questions
const question = document.getElementById('question');
const options = Array.from(document.getElementsByClassName('option-text'));
const progressText = document.getElementById('proress-text');
const scoreTest = document.getElementById('score');
const progressBarFull = document.getElementById('progress-bar-full');
const nextButton = document.getElementById('next');
const totalScores = document.getElementById('final-score');


let currentQuestion = {};
let acceptingAnswers = true;
let score = 0;
let questionCounter = 0;
let availableQuestions = [];
let answerOption;

let questions = [
  {
    question: 'What object is used to access globally scoped variables in a browser, for a front-end web application?',
    options: ['Window', 'Browser', 'Document', 'Global'],
    answer: 0
  },

  {
    question: 'Which one of the following sedimentary basin is related to extension?',
    options: ['Half-graben', 'Foredeep', 'fore-arc', 'piggyback'],
    answer: 0
  },

  {
    question: 'In seismic session, paraconformity is marked by?',
    options: ['onlap', 'downlap', 'erosional-truncation', 'concordance'],
    answer: 3
  },

  {
    question: 'To use flexbox we define a container as a flexbox. What is the CSS to do this?',
    options: [
      'position:absolute;',
      'float:left;', 
      'display:flex;', 
      'display:block;'
    ],
    answer: 2
  },

  {
    question: 'What is the array prototype method that changes the contents of an array by removing existing elements and/or adding new elements?',
    options: ['[].remove()', '[].slice()', '[].splice()', '[].delete()'],
    answer: 2
  },

  {
    question: 'How would you indicate that you are neutral as to when or in what order a particular script is loaded, relative to other scripts?',
    options: [
      'Add the async attribute', 
      'Add the sync attribute with a value of false', 
      'Add the defer attribute', 
      'Add the defer attribute with a value of false'
    ],
    answer: 0
  },

  {
    question: 'What is the correct escape notation for a new line in a string?',
    options: ['/n/', '\\n', '/newline', '/n'],
    answer: 1
  },

  {
    question: 'Which primitive type represents the intentional absence of any object value?',
    options: ['‘’', 'Error', 'undefined', 'null'],
    answer: 3
  },

  {
    question: 'The shape of the earth is best describe as?',
    options: ['spheriod', 'prolate ellipsoid', 'ellipsoid', 'oblate spheriod'],
    answer: 3
  },

  {
    question: 'Which ine amongst the following is the CORRECT attitude of a bed?',
    options: ['21°, 95°', 'N45°W, 40°SE', ' 090°/20°W', '089°, 75°S'],
    answer: 3 
  },

  {
    question: 'In which one of the following configurations are the electrodes uniformly spaced?',
    options: ['Schlumberger array', 'Pole-Dipole array', ' Wenner array', 'Pole-pole array'],
    answer: 2
  },

  {
    question: 'In triclinic crystal system, the three crystallographic axes a,b,c are of?',
    options: [
      'Equal lengths with angle between b and c as 90°', 
      'Equal lengths with angle between a and c not equal 90°', 
      'Unequal lengths with angle between a and c not equal 90°', 
      'Unequal lengths with angle between b and c as 90°'
    ],
    answer: 2
  },

  {
    question: 'Hawaiian Island chain is the result of?',
    options: [
      'collision of two oceanic plate', 
      'intraplate hot spot activity', 
      'divergence of two oceanic plate', 
      'interplate hot spot activity'
    ],
    answer: 1 
  },

  {
    question: 'A land fall that results from free fall of rocks is called?',
    options: ['talus slope', 'eskers', 'alluvial fan', 'debris flow'],
    answer: 0 
  },

  {
    question: 'Which of the following logging methods is NOT used to determine porosity?',
    options: ['Sonic', 'SP', 'Neutron', 'Gamma-gamma'],
    answer: 1
  },

  {
    question: `Gardner's formula relates the seismic P-waves to?`,
    options: ['Permeability', 'Lithology', 'Porosity', 'Density'],
    answer: 3
  },

  {
    question: 'PcP and ScS phases are reflected from?',
    options: [
      'Crust - mantle boundary', 
      'Core - mantle boundary', 
      'Inner core - outer core boundary', 
      'Lithosphere - asthenosphere boundary'
    ],
    answer: 1
  },

  {
    question: 'Identify the CORRECT sequence of the electromagnetic waves in their increasing frequency',
    options: [
      'Radiowave, microwave, infrared, visible, ultra violet, X-ray', 
      'Radiowave, infrared, microwave, visible, ultra violet, X-ray', 
      'Radiowave, microwave, X-ray, infrared, visible, ultra violet ', 
      'infrared, Radiowave, microwave, ultra violet, visible, X-ray'
    ],
    answer: 0
  }
]    

// constants
const CORRECT_SCORES = 20;
const MAX_QUESTIONS = 5;


const startGame = () => {
  questionCounter = 0;
  score = 0;
  availableQuestions = [...questions]
  getNewQuestion();
};

const getNewQuestion = () => {
  if(availableQuestions.length === 0 || questionCounter >= MAX_QUESTIONS) {
    // store user score
    localStorage.setItem('score', score);

    // go to the end page
    return location.href = 'end.html';
  };

  questionCounter++;
  progressText.innerText =`Question: ${questionCounter}/${MAX_QUESTIONS}`;
  // updating the progress bar
  progressBarFull.style.width = `${(questionCounter / MAX_QUESTIONS) * 100}%`;

  const questionIndex = Math.floor(Math.random() * availableQuestions.length);
  currentQuestion = availableQuestions[questionIndex];
  question.innerText = currentQuestion.question;

  options.forEach(option => {
    const number = option.dataset['number'];
    option.innerText = currentQuestion.options[number];
  });

  availableQuestions.splice(questionIndex, 1);

  acceptingAnswers = true;
};

const incrementScore = num => {
  score += num;
  scoreTest.innerText = score;
}

let selectedOption, correctAnswer, option;

options.forEach(option => {
  option.addEventListener('click', e => {
    e.preventDefault();

    if(!acceptingAnswers) return; 

    acceptingAnswers = false;
    selectedOption = e.target;
    const selectedAnswer = selectedOption.dataset['number'];
    const correctOption = options.filter(opt => currentQuestion.answer == opt.getAttribute('data-number'))
    correctAnswer = correctOption[0]


    if (selectedAnswer == currentQuestion.answer) {
      option.parentElement.classList.add('correct');
      option.classList.add('child-color');
    } else {
      option.parentElement.classList.add('incorrect');
      option.classList.add('child-color');
      correctAnswer.parentElement.classList.add('correct');
      correctAnswer.classList.add('child-color')
    }

    const classToApply = selectedAnswer == currentQuestion.answer ? 'correct' : 'incorrect';

    if (classToApply === 'correct') {
      incrementScore(CORRECT_SCORES);
    }
  });
});

nextButton.addEventListener('click', e => {

  selectedOption.parentElement.classList.remove('incorrect')
  correctAnswer.parentElement.classList.remove('correct')
  correctAnswer.classList.remove('child-color')
  selectedOption.classList.remove('child-color');
  getNewQuestion()
})

startGame();


// EndGame();

